<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<instructiontext>
  <!-- The height is the pixels of the panel containing this document.  It determines how much scrollable space
  there is. -->
  <height>890</height>
  <text>
    <h>Note to First Time Users</h>
    <p>To complete this activity, you need to be able to read a seismic wave travel-time curve. If you are
      unfamiliar with travel-time curves, you should complete the Travel-Time exercise before continuing with
      Epicenter Location and Magnitude.</p>
    <h>Epicenter Location</h>
    <p>The <glossary term="epicenter">epicenter</glossary> of an earthquake is the spot on the earth's
      surface directly above the quake's <glossary term="focus">focus</glossary>.  It can be the site of much
      damage. When an earthquake occurs, we don't initially know the location of its epicenter. But we do
      have access to the <glossary term="seismograms">seismograms</glossary> that recorded the exact times of
      arrival of the <glossary term="p+waves">P</glossary> and <glossary term="s+waves">S waves</glossary> at
      seismic stations at known locations. The difference between the times of arrival of S and P waves is
      called the <glossary term="S-P lag time">S-P lag time</glossary>. In the <glossary
        term="travel-time+curve">"Travel-Time" curve</glossary> activity, you constructed a graph that now
      can be used to determine the distance between a seismic station and the earthquake's epicenter.</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, just knowing the distance from a seismic station to an epicenter is not enough
      information to actually locate the epicenter. You also need to know the map direction of the epicenter
      from the seismic station. But there is a way around this problem by using a technique called
      "triangulation," which uses the S-P lag times recorded at three different seismic stations. A
      travel-time curve is used to convert the S-P lag times to distances. In this activity you will draw
      circles around each station with the radius of each circle equal to the epicentral distance. The three
      circles will intersect at the epicenter.</p>
    <p>The three circles will probably not intersect at one exact point, but should come pretty close. You
      may have to visually interpolate more precisely to pinpoint your epicenter. Discounting measurement
      errors, there are other factors that affect the speed of earthquake waves (and your determination of on
      epicenter.).  For example, variations in the rock types through which the waves travel will change the
      actual travel times and hence the S-P intervals, which in turn, will produce small, but significant
      variations in the epicentral distances. We should not expect the method of triangulation to result in
      an exact point.</p>
    <h>Magnitude Determination</h>
    <p>Magnitude is a quantitative measurement of the energy released by an earthquake.  Magnitude helps
      scientists answer questions such as: "How strong was this particular earthquake and how does it compare
      to other earthquakes?"</p>
    <p>Professor Charles Richter developed the first widely used magnitude scale in 1935. Richter's
      magnitude, also known as local magnitude, was developed using southern California earthquake data.
      Richter defined the magnitude of a local earthquake as the logarithm to the base 10 of the maximum
      seismic wave <glossary term="amplitude">amplitude</glossary> (Amax, measured in millimeters) as
      recorded on a standard seismograph at a distance of exactly 100 km from the epicenter. Because of wave
      attenuation, stations closer than 100 km to the epicenter measure higher values of Amax, while those
      farther away, measure lower values. Therefore, Richter magnitude determinations include a correction
      for distance to epicenter.</p>
    <p>Richter used a logarithmic function because maximum amplitudes vary substantially.  As a consequence
      of the logarithmic scale, when magnitude increases by 1 unit, Amax increases 10 times. Richter
      magnitude is used at seismograph stations located less than about 500 km from the epicenters of
      earthquakes with magnitudes less than 6.</p>
    <p>The Richter magnitude of an earthquake is a number: about 3 for nearby earthquakes that are strong
      enough for people to feel and about 8 for the Earth's strongest earthquakes. The most sensitive
      seismographs can record nearby earthquakes with magnitudes of about negative 2, which is the equivalent
      of stamping your foot on the floor.</p>
    <p>Today, numerous magnitude scales other than Richter's are in use. Here are some examples:</p>
    <p extraspacing="0">- <glossary term="P+Wave+Magnitude">P Wave magnitude</glossary> (mb) is useful for deep-focus earthquakes.</p>
    <p extraspacing="0">- <glossary term="Surface+Wave+Magnitude">Surface Wave Magnitude</glossary> (Ms) is favored for shallow-focus earthquakes</p>
    <p>- <glossary term="Moment+Magnitude">Moment Magnitude</glossary> (MW) is most favored overall because it takes into account the surface area of
      fault rupture.</p>
    <p>Reference: Bolt, Bruce A., 1999, Earthquakes, 4th edition, Freeman and Co.</p>
  </text>
</instructiontext>
