<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<instructiontext>
  <height>475</height>
  <!-- The height is the pixels of the panel containing this document.  It
  determines how much scrollable space there is. -->
  <text>
    <h>Assignment: Detemining Epicenter and Magnitude </h>

    <p>First read the &quot;Background&quot; material.</p>

    <p>Your objective now is to locate the epicenter of an earthquake and estimate its Richter magnitude. If you don't
      know a term, return to the Background and use the Glossary for clarification.</p>

    <p number="1.">Start by clicking on &quot;Select Earthquake&quot; tool on line 1 of Tasks. Select one of the
      options for the location of an earthquake (given in the right-hand column): Northern or Southern California,
      Utah, or random (where the program chooses a region.)</p>

    <p number="2.">Click the &quot;Trigger Earthquake&quot; button on the map to generate an earthquake and its
      seismograms.  Other tools will give information about its purpose. With these tools, do the following tasks in
      the order given in the task menu (to see the task menu, click on the &quot;task&quot; or check mark tool):</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="a.">measure the S-P lag times for 3 stations</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="b.">find the distances from the epicenter</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="c.">measure the maximum S-wave amplitude</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="d.">draw circles on the map to triangulate to the epicenter</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="e.">locate the epicenter on the map</p>

    <p extraspacing="2" indentlevel="20" number="f.">estimate the latitude and longitude of your earthquake's
      epicenter</p>

    <p indentlevel="20" number="g.">estimate your earthquake's magnitude</p>

    <p>As you progress, be sure to enter your results into the Journal's data table.</p>


    <p number="3.">After you determine the magnitude and the latitude and longitude of the epicenter, you will be given
      a quiz and a Certificate of Completion. </p>

    <p>At any time, you may save your work and return later to finish. You may also print parts of the activity: the
      backgound statement, the assignment, the map, and your journal entries.</p>

  </text>
</instructiontext>
