<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<instructiontext>
  <!-- The height is the pixels of the panel containing this document.  It determines how much scrollable space
  there is. -->
  <height>660</height>
  <text>
    <h>Information on Historical Earthquakes</h>

    <p>Three of the earthquakes in this activity are based upon historical earthquakes. Below you'll find more
      information on these earthquakes.</p>

    <h>Northridge Earthquake of 1994</h>

    <p>At 4:31 A.M., Pacific Standard Time, on Monday, January 17, a moderate but very damaging earthquake with a
      moment magnitude (Mw) of 6.7 struck the densely populated San Fernando Valley, in northern Los Angeles.  This
      region has been repeatedly rocked by moderate to large earthquakes throughout recorded history.  Thousands of
      aftershocks, many in the magnitude 4.0 to 5.0 range, occurred during the next few weeks, further damaging
      already-affected structures.</p>

    <p>The death toll was 57, and more than 1,500 people were seriously injured.  A few days after the earthquake,
      9,000 homes and businesses were still without electricity; 20,000 were without gas; and more than 48,500 had
      little or no water.  About 12,500 structures were moderately to severely damaged, leaving thousands of people
      temporarily homeless.  Of the 66,546 buildings inspected, 6% were severely damaged (red tagged) and 17% were
      moderately damaged (yellow tagged.)  Major freeway damage occurred up to 32 km from the epicenter.  Collapses and
      other severe damage forced closure of portions of 11 major roads to downtown Los Angeles.</p>

    <h>Loma Prieta Earthquake of 1989</h>

    <p>At 5:04 P.M., Tuesday, October 17, 1989, as over 62,000 fans filled Candlestick Park for the third game of the
      World Series and the San Francisco Bay Area commute moved into its heaviest flow, a Richter magnitude 7.1
      earthquake struck.  It was an emergency planner's worst-case scenario.  The 20-second earthquake was centered
      about 60 miles south of San Francisco, and was felt as far away as San Diego and western Nevada.  Scientists had
      predicted an earthquake would hit on this section of the San Andreas Fault and considered it one of the Bay
      Area's most dangerous stretches of the fault.  Damage was in the billions of dollars range.</p>

    <h>Hansel Valley Earthquake of 1934</h>

    <p>1934 Hansel Valley earthquake, north of the Great Salt Lake, magnitude 6.6, a sparsely populated area.  Two
      people were killed.  Property damage was limited mainly to downed chimneys and cracked walls in poorly
      constructed brick buildings.  This quake was felt in Idaho, Montana, Nevada, and Wyoming.  Although a minor quake
      at the time, the increased population in this area now makes earthquakes in this region potentially more
      destructive.</p>

  </text>
</instructiontext>
